מזל טוב *Mazel tov*, today's דף *daf* is מ"ד *Mem Dalet* 44
and we pick up in the middle of מ"ג עמוד ב' *Mem
Gimmel Amud Bet*. You know what, we'll start from the top of
מ"ג עמוד ב' *Mem Gimmel Amud Bet*, תנו רבנן *Tanu Rabbanan*, three
lines in. תנו רבנן *Tanu Rabbanan*: מכר לו בית מכר לו שדה
*machar lo bayit machar lo sadeh*. So we were discussing the whole
issue about can you be a witness on somebody's ownership of a
piece of land if you might be a direct or indirect beneficiary?
Well, you can't, but the idea is to determine whether you might
be an indirect beneficiary. So it says תנו רבנן *Tanu Rabbanan*: מכר
לו בית מכר לו שדה *machar lo bayit machar lo sadeh*, if
ראובן Reuven *Reuven* sells to שמעון Shimon *Shimon* a house or a
field, אין מעיד לו עליה ein meid lo aleha, *ein me'id lo
aleha*. And then there's a challenge to that ownership of that field,
ראובן Reuven. *Reuven* cannot testify that it belongs to שמעון Shimon *Shimon*,
מפני שאחריותו עליו mifnei she-achrayuto alav, *mipnei she-achrayuto alav*, because he'll be
responsible for it. So presumably what that means he'll be responsible for
it is that שמעון Shimon *Shimon* will want his money back. Okay,
so that makes sense. So that's why ראובן Reuven *Reuven* can't be
testify. Now, but then it goes on to say מכר לו פרה
מכר לו טלית *machar lo parah machar lo talit*, let's say he
sold him something that was chattel, a cow or garment, מעיד meid
לו עליה *me'id lo aleha*. Then ראובן Reuven *Reuven* can testify that
it properly belongs to שמעון Shimon *Shimon* after he sold it to
שמעון Shimon *Shimon*, מפני mifnei שאין אחריותו עליו achrayuto alav *mipnei she-ein
achrayuto alav*, because he's not responsible for it. So the גמרא Gemara,
*Gemara* initially says: what are you talking about? If it turns out
that ראובן Reuven's *Reuven* held it unjustly and the sale was never
a sale, so in either case, whether it's land or whether it's
chattel, שמעון Shimon *Shimon* can go back to ראובן Reuven *Reuven* ask
for his money back. So ראובן Reuven *Reuven* should not be believed
to testify. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says מאי mai? שנא רישא
ומאי שנא סיפא *mai shna resha u-mai shna seifa*, how is the
beginning different than the end? So אמר רב ששת *Amar Rav Sheshet*:
רישא בראובן *resha be-Reuven*, my voice really, רישא *resha*, so the first
thing, I'm sorry, trying to get my voice. אמר רב ששת *Amar
Rav Sheshet*: רישא בראובן שגזל שדה משמעון ומכרה ללוי *resha be-Reuven she-gazal
sadeh mi-Shimon u-machra le-Levi*, ואתה יהודה Yehuda? וקא מערער *v'ata Yehuda v'ka
m'arer*. So this is going to be very complicated and to relieve
you of this, this is not only a complicated scenario, it's a
very hard read of this ברייתא Baraita, *Baraita* and we're not going
to stick with it. So in the end we're going to have
a much, much simpler read of this ברייתא braisa. *Baraita*, but now
you'll
just deal with this and we're going to figure out what the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s attempted explanation is, okay? So
ראובן Reuven *Reuven*, so what's the case? ראובן Reuven שגזל שדה משמעון
*Reuven she-gazal sadeh mi-Shimon*, okay here's שמעון Shimon *Shimon*, he is the
rightful owner of the field, okay? ראובן Reuven *Reuven* stole that field,
okay he was גזל *gazal*, okay, and then ראובן Reuven שגזל שדה
משמעון ומכרה ללוי *Reuven she-gazal sadeh mi-Shimon u-machra le-Levi*, and then he
sold it to לוי Levi, *Levi*. Okay, so ואתה יהודה Yehuda וקא
מערער *v'ata Yehuda v'ka m'arer*. Now this other guy יהודה Yehuda? *Yehuda*
comes here and he says: that's mine, okay? That's mine.
Okay now,
so everybody got the case? Yes. Okay, so now דלא ליזיל שמעון
Shimon לאסהודי ליה ללוי *de-lo leizel Shimon le-asodei lei le-Levi*. Now the
point is, the phrase in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is, what's the
phrase in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*? The phrase in the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* is מכר לו בית אין מעיד meid עליו *machar lo bayit
ein me'id alav*, מכר לו בית אין מעיד עליו
*machar lo bayit ein me'id alav*, מפני שאחריותו עליו mifnei she-achrayuto alav.
*mipnei she-achrayuto alav*. We're going to have a really wild reinterpretation of
those words. So okay, ראובן Reuven
*Reuven*... so now the question is, יהודה Yehuda. *Yehuda* says it's mine.
Can שמעון Shimon *Shimon*, who is the original owner of the field,
come and say that no, that's not יהודה Yehuda. *Yehuda*'s? Is he,
does he have a vested interest in that? Because שמעון Shimon *Shimon*'s
going to want eventually to get his field back, right? So if
he's going to want to get his field back, he's either going
to have to try to get it back from לוי Levi, *Levi*
and prove it's his, or if יהודה Yehuda *Yehuda* wins this case
with לוי Levi *Levi*, he's going to have to get it back
from יהודה Yehuda *Yehuda* and prove that it's his. Okay, שמעון Shimon
*Shimon* eventually is going to want to get it back. So since
שמעון Shimon *Shimon* is eventually going to want to get it back,
maybe he can be believed to testify it's not יהודה Yehuda *Yehuda*'s
since anyway he's going to have to get it back from לוי
Levi *Levi*, like why should it matter, right? He's trying to get
his field back anyway. So we'll see why it matters in a
minute but let's first explain how the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* explains now
this ברייתא braisa *Baraita*, it's very bizarre. מכר לו בית *machar lo
bayit* means ראובן Reuven? *Reuven* sold the field to לוי Levi, *Levi*.
אין מעיד עליו *ein me'id alav* is שמעון Shimon *Shimon*. שמעון Shimon
*Shimon* can't testify about that field. Okay, completely switching who we're talking
about. מפני שאחריותו עליו mifnei she-achrayuto alav. *mipnei she-achrayuto alav* and the
word אחריותו *achrayuto* here means something it never means, which the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara*'s going to say later, it doesn't mean he's responsible for
it, but it means because somehow he's got like a stake in
the issue. Because שמעון Shimon *Shimon* has a stake in this, he
cannot testify about it. So it's a very bad read of the
ברייתא *Baraita*, but let's now work through the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* about
what the issue is. Like if you... so let's take a look.
So דלא ליזיל שמעון Shimon, לאסהודי ליה ללוי *de-lo leizel Shimon le-asodei
lei le-Levi*, שמעון Shimon *Shimon* can't go to testify on behalf of
לוי Levi? *Levi*, דניחא ליה דהדרא *de-nicha lei de-hadra*, because he wants
it to remain. in the hands of לוי. Levi. Why?
So we'll see in a minute why. I mean, in the end
of the day, even if he's going to have to get it
back from לוי, Levi, what difference does it make if he gets
it back from לוי, Levi, he gets it back from יהודה? Yehuda.
But before we get to that, we're going to ask an interim
question. One minute, says the גמרא, Gemara if he's going to be
able to prove it's not יהודה's Yehuda in order to help out
this case, that's the question, can he help out this case and
prove it? So presumably that's by proving it's his. So of course
he can bring witness, you know, or what if he is himself
the עד, ed, excuse me, then of course... well let's take a
look. Okay, וכיון דאסהיד ליה דלוי הוא היכי מצי מפיק ליה מיניה?
Vekivan de-asei lei de-Levi hu, heichi mati matpalei minei? Oh,
I'm sorry, it's not that. So first the גמרא's Gemara's point is,
so can שמעון Shimon come and testify that it's לוי's Levi to
get it out of the hands of יהודה? Yehuda? The point is
no, because he stands to gain, we'll see how he stands to
gain in a minute, okay? But he can't testify for לוי Levi.
to get it out of the hands of יהודה. Yehuda. So the
גמרא's Gemara first question is one minute, as soon as he himself
is going to be a witness and testify that it belongs to
לוי, Levi. he's making a statement that it does not belong to
who? Him. Okay, so how could he have any stake in this,
right? Why shouldn't he be able to testify it belongs to לוי?
Levi, He's basically giving up any claim and any stake by testifying
it belongs to לוי. Levi, So why do you give up a
claim without doing that in writing?
Yeah, because if once you testify to something in court, that's an
implicit admission that it's not yours.
So why shouldn't שמעון Shimon, be allowed to testify it belongs to
לוי, Levi right? That he's basically saying with that testimony it doesn't
belong to him. Maybe he's not testifying... so that's what
the גמרא's Gemara going to say. Okay, וכיון דאסהיד ליה דלוי הוא
היכי מצי מפיק ליה מיניה? Vekivan de-asei lei de-Levi hu, heichi mati
mapik lei minei? So no, דאמר de'amar no, this is what David
I'm sure was about to say, ידענא דהאי ארעא דלאו יהודה היא.
yadana dehai ara delav Yehuda hi. No, no, no. His testimony is
not that it belongs to לוי, Levi his testimony is: I will
bring, I and some other witness, because you need two witnesses, right?
Will testify that we know that it couldn't belong to יהודה. Yehuda
I don't know the exact scenario they're able to testify to a
negative, but we're not going to worry about that, okay? So he
can testify, he's not saying it is לוי's, Levi he's saying it's
not יהודה's. Yehuda. Now, why is that not a good testimony? What
does he gain? So good, it's not in the hands of יהודה
Yehuda. now, it's in the hands of לוי. Levi So what's his
gain from it? It's still not his yet. One minute, ובהא זכותא,
ubeha zechuta, so the גמרא Gemara first says one minute, ובהא זכותא
דקא מפיק ליה ללוי ליפיק מיהודה. ubeha zechuta de-ka mapik lei le-Levi
leifik mi-Yehuda. So the
גמרא Gemara says I don't get it. Okay, he can't testify because
now it's not going to be if he were to testify it
wouldn't be יהודה's Yehuda it would go to לוי. Levi, Okay, but
he's still going to have to get it from לוי, Levi. right?
So whatever proof he's going to have that it's his that's going
to let him win the court case from לוי, Levi let him
bring that same proof to win the court case from יהודה. Yehuda
So why does he gain by taking it out of the hands
of יהודה Yehuda and having לוי Levi? get it, right? If at
the end of the day he's going to have to prove it's
his? Right? And if at the end of the day he's going
to have to prove it's his, so what difference does it make
if he's proving that against לוי Levi, or against יהודה? Yehuda One
minute, so let's see what the גמרא's Gemara answer is. So the
גמרא Gemara, says דאמר de'amar no, השני נוח לי הראשון קשה הימנו.
hasheini noach li harishon kasheh mimenu. It's easier... right, we had that
before, well we discussed it before. It's easier for me to win
a court case against שמעון Shimon than it is against יהודה. Yehuda's
Okay, יהודה's Yehuda's, got all these fancy corporate lawyers against יהודה. Yehuda's,
No, I mean it's easier for me to win against, oh, against
לוי Levi, than against יהודה. Yehuda Okay,
you know, יהודה's Yehuda got this great team of lawyers, even if
I'm totally in the right I'm going to lose, לוי Levi. I'm
going to be, it's going to be easier for me to win
from. So given that it's possible he's going to want to take
one of them to court to get his field back, but because
he's got a stake in the question of who is he going
to have to bring to court eventually, he cannot testify in a
way that determines whether it goes to יהודה Yehuda or לוי, Levi.
because we know that he's going to want to get that field
back for himself, and it might matter to him who his opponent
is going to be. Okay, that's the basic answer. So at the
end of the day it's a complicated case, but the point is
a pretty simple one. You can't testify in a debate here between
these two people if at the end of the day you're going
to want to try to win that field back, and it might
matter to you who you're fighting against at the end. Okay? All
right, so that's pretty clear at least the issues that are at
stake. I mean it's a hard read of this ברייתא, but that's
the basic point. So now let's see what the גמרא Gemara says,
ואיבעית אימא, ve-iba'it eima,
if you want you can say, כגון דאיכא סהדי למר ואיכא סהדי
למר, kigon de-ika sahadei le-mar ve-ika sahadei le-mar, ואמרי רבנן היכא ארעא
היכא דקיימא תיקום. ve-amrei rabbanan heich ara heicha de-kaima teiku. So I
don't know if this makes it easier or harder, but it basically
says: here's the story, יהודה Yehuda, has two witnesses to say that
it's his,
okay, and שמעון Shimon. has two witnesses to say that it's his.
So what are we going to do if there's a... if there's
contradictory witnesses? So by case of land, you know this gets back
to all those earlier גמרות, Gemaras, כל דאלים גבר kol dalim gevar
and so on, two against two, we're just not going to get
involved. Whoever is in possession of it can stay in possession of
it. So therefore basically, but Which either set of witness makes it
clear that it doesn't belong to who in this scenario? ראובן Reuven
*Reuven* or לוי Levi. *Levi*. Well, right. Okay, so here's the story.
If I, שמעון Shimon *Shimon*, sit this case out and let יהודה
Yehuda *Yehuda* win it from לוי Levi *Levi*, okay, then even after
later when I bring my two witnesses to show that it's mine,
it's going to stay in the possession of יהודה Yehuda *Yehuda*. It's
going to be two against two and it's going to stay in
the possession of יהודה Yehuda *Yehuda*. Okay, but if I get involved
right now and somehow manage to within this debate—I can't deal with
these witnesses, but again, I can't figure out the exact details, but
we have to assume that this is going to try to work.
Within this debate, I'm going to be able to make יהודה Yehuda
*Yehuda* lose and make, and you know, and make לוי Levi *Levi*
win, because for some reason these witnesses are not relevant for this
debate. Okay, then I'm going to be able to take it from
לוי Levi. *Levi*, because my witnesses say that it's mine, and then
when he tries to come and produce his witnesses, right, I'll already
be in my possession. So it's another scenario where where basically שמעון
Shimon, *Shimon* says, "I stand to gain by testifying in this case.
It'll make it easier for me to reclaim that field than if
I let יהודה Yehuda *Yehuda* first win this case, then it's going
to be harder for me to reclaim the field." Okay? Yes. Can
we imagine like the case is like the marriage case? And I'm
trying to see whether, you know, if it was like one of
those cases where neither party wins?
Meaning between יהודה Yehuda *Yehuda* and לוי Levi, *Levi*. And we sort
of use like we split it or something? No, no, no, because
remember when we had a case where the woman says that you
have to give me everything in order to marry me and then
he gives a second contract to the son, etc., that we say
that neither one gets it, right? Yeah, but that was different. That
was because... What I'm suggesting is that something like that, if you
have something like that between יהודה Yehuda *Yehuda* and לוי *Levi*, right,
so יהודה *Yehuda* has witnesses that somehow שמעון Shimon *Shimon* gave it
to him, right, but... All right, this is getting too complicated. I'm
going to have to move on. Okay, anyway, the basic point is,
is that we read this ברייתא *Baraita* in a strange way, made
it a very complicated case with all these different players, but the
basic point is שמעון Shimon *Shimon* can't testify because—and oh, we haven't
explained why land is different than מטלטלין metaltelin, *metaltelin*, right? The whole
thing that was—the whole thing that was pushing us to try to
create this case was because the ברייתא *Baraita* said in this case
שמעון Shimon *Shimon* can't testify, but if it was about a cow
or garment, he could. So we have—we're going to have to figure
out why that's going to make it different, okay? So we've created
this complicated case. Let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says, ואוקמה בגזלן *V'ukmah b'gazlan*... So if this is really what the
author of the ברייתא *Baraita* wanted to tell us, why did it
have to introduce לוי *Levi*? Why didn't they just say that it's
this case? There's only a גזלן gazlan, *gazlan* from שמעון Shimon *Shimon*,
יהודה *Yehuda*'s trying to get it back, יהודה *Yehuda*'s saying it's always
his. So again, שמעון Shimon. *Shimon* can't get into this argument because
that's going to make it easier for him to win against ראובן
Reuven *Reuven*, right? Who had to introduce
a case of sale? That seems to be completely unnecessary. Okay, because
the basic point is, whatever the debate is between יהודה *Yehuda* and
whoever, שמעון Shimon. *Shimon* can't get involved. So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, "Ah, that's what—that's what makes us—allows us to
make a distinction between land and chattel. דבעי למתני סיפא מכר לו
פרה מכר לו טלית *D'ba'i l'misni seifa makhar lo para makhar lo
talit*... If it wasn't land, if it was a cow or a
garment, in that case שמעון Shimon *Shimon* can get involved. Why can
שמעון Shimon, *Shimon* get involved in that case? דדווקא מכר מכר דהוי
ליה יאוש ושינוי רשות ye'ush v'shinui reshus, *D'davka makhar makhir d'havei lei
ye'ush v'shinui reshut*... Only if he sold it, because then there is
יאוש ye'ush *ye'ush*—you have given up hope for getting it back—and a
change in possession. אבל לא מכר *Aval lo makhar*—if it was just
stolen and not sold—דהדרא ליה לא *de'hadra lei lo*—and it would not...
So now we're saying why chattel would be different. If it were
just this case and we were saying שמעון Shimon *Shimon* can't get
involved between יהודה *Yehuda* and ראובן Reuven *Reuven* because he stands to
gain, it wouldn't matter what he stole. If he stole land or
he stole a cow, either way
if he interferes with this case, it'll be easier for him to
retrieve it, right? Same point. It wouldn't matter whether it would be
land or whether it would be chattel. But if he sold it,
okay, so if it's land, we already saw, he's going to gain,
he'd rather fight לוי *Levi* than fight יהודה *Yehuda*. But what if
it were not land? What if it was a cow? So what
happens if it's a cow? It gets stolen from ראובן Reuven *Reuven*
and then there's something called יאוש ye'ush? *ye'ush*. He gives up hope
of getting it back. But if it's still in the hands of
the גזלן gazlan *gazlan* even after he's given up hope, he can
still retrieve it. But then the גזלן gazlan *gazlan* sold it to
לוי *Levi*. That's יאוש ye'ush? *ye'ush* and שינוי רשות shinui reshus. *shinui
reshut*, a change of possession. So now, you know who owns that
cow right now? Even if you could a hundred percent prove that
it always belonged to שמעון Shimon *Shimon* and ראובן Reuven *Reuven* stole
it and sold it to לוי *Levi*, who owns the cow right
now? לוי *Levi*. That's the rule of
יאוש ye'ush *ye'ush* and שינוי רשות *shinui reshut*. So in that case,
he can get involved in this debate
and
testify." Okay so that is the difference now between chattel and land.
Okay, by land he can't testify cause he'll eventually be able to
get his land back cause the idea of יאוש ye'ush, doesn't apply
by land because land is always like there, there's fundamentally there's an
idea that קרקע karka isn't stolen in the same way, although there's
an interesting תוספות Tosfos that says that יאוש could apply by land,
but we're going to assume it doesn't. Okay, so if it's land,
since land doesn't change physically hands and it's not taken away and
stolen in the same way, he'll always be able to get his
land back, so he can't interfere with this debate. But by a
cow, once it's stolen and changed possession, יאוש ושינוי רשות, ye'ush v'shinui
reshus, he's not getting it back, so what difference does it make
if he gets involved in that debate? He's never getting his cow
back anyway. Why would he want to get involved? Why want cow
back?
That's exactly the point, no, 'cause he just wants to be a
good citizen and testify to something he knows. I know evidence. Right?
He's not doing it because he has a vested interest. That's my
cow though. Oh, I see. He's... could be anyway. Okay, what can
I tell you? So before it was sold there was no יאוש?
Right. And he'd have to pay because you know if he testifies
that ראובן Reuven, stole it, doesn't he stand to gain four or
five? If only there was no יאוש? Yeah, but he's not testifying
that he stole it. He's testifying whether it's between יהודה and לוי.
Yeah, he would stand to gain about testimony about this, but that's
not what's being discussed. Thank you very much, what's being discussed? What's
the context? Can he testify that it's not יהודה's to allow לוי
to win the case? That's the question. Which then he doesn't get
four or five? It's not material to whether he gets four or
five. Oh, you're saying that if he testifies that it was always
his then he stands to gain well that's similar to a question
the גמרא Gemara is going to ask. You're asking about compensation, right?
Now we're talking about ownership of the cow, but you're saying he
might stand to gain from the compensation perspective. Okay, we're going to
get back, that's גמרא's Gemara question. Hold on. Yeah. So here's a
case like this where this שמעון Shimon, has got evidence that he
can testify about the original ownership of the cow. Is he obligated
to bring that? So that's yeah, that's a whole discussion in the
גמרא Gemara, מסכת שבועות, Masechet Shavuos, there's a שבועת העדות, Shvuas Ha'eidus,
there's a whole discussion about a חיוב hiyuv to testify and somebody
could be משביע... mashbia... yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah. That's a separate
discussion about a חיוב hiyuv to testify. Okay, let's go on. So
the גמרא Gemara says... All right. So... okay guys, I need your
cooperation today. Okay, so no, I'm sorry. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says like this. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, now the גמרא
Gemara is going to ask essentially Michael's question. וסיפא נמי, V'seifa nami,
says the גמרא, Gemara one minute. Okay, so... אבל לא מכרה דהדרא
ליה ליה. aval lo machra de'hadra lei leilei. So that's why by
chattel it matters that it was sold, because that's why he can
testify because he's not getting it back. So תנא רישא נמי מכרה.
tanna reisha nami machra. So therefore we're talking about the case of
selling it. That allows us to distinguish between land and chattel. So
the גמרא Gemara says: וסיפא נמי, V'seifa nami, ניהי דמיאש מגופיה, nihi
de'miya'ish migufeih, מדמי מי
מיאש? midamei mi miya'ish?
So the גמרא Gemara says that, which is essentially Michael's question which
is: Okay, so wonderful, in this case he has lost the cow.
But you know what he can still do? He can still get
paid back for the cow. How do you get paid back for
the cow? I'll tell you in a minute. Okay, but he can
get paid back for the cow. So it really does matter whether
it was always יהודה's, was it originally שמעון Shimon. stole from him
and then sold to לוי? Because if it was always יהודה's, he's
not getting paid for the cow. If he's able to get it
out of the hands of יהודה and establish the fact that it
was stolen from him and sold to לוי, then he's getting paid
back for the cow. Right? So therefore he shouldn't be able to
get involved here either, 'cause he's going to matter that it's going
to matter by getting יהודה out of the picture, it's going to
let him get compensated from ראובן. Reuven All right? So the question
is so point is: ניהי דמיאש מגופיה, nihi de'miya'ish migufeih, fine, there
was יאוש on the about the body of the cow itself, so
the cow he's lost. מדמי מי מיאש? midamei mi miya'ish? He's not
given up hope of getting back the money. דמים Dami like money?
Yeah. So the גמרא Gemara says... of course, the first year when
I was 17 years old and went to Israel for the first
time and the only Hebrew I'd ever really been exposed to was
in the גמרא Gemara and I went to a store and I
said "אין לי דמים." ein li damim. I don't have... I wanted
to say "מכסף," mi'kesef, I don't have money, but I always... anyway,
fine. Okay.
I think you were definitely... I feel for you. I know exactly
where you were and I feel for the shopkeeper. Okay. מדמי מי
מיאש? Midamei mi miya'ish? So the גמרא Gemara
says: No. צריכא דמית ליה גזלן. Tzricha d'meit lei gazlan. The גזלן,
the גזלן died. ראובן Reuven died. Now here's an interesting הלכה. halacha.
ראובן Reuven steals something, he dies. Can שמעון Shimon get compensated for
what was stolen from the kids? Okay. Now, it might have to
do with a question about like, does that create a lien on
ראובן's Reuven estate? Maybe if ראובן Reuven had land and property and
he stole, that created a debt, right? That created a lien on
the estate and he can collect from the lien on the estate,
right? So that's an interesting question. Let's let's bracket that. Let's assume
that he did not leave over any land or property or any
estate. or whatever. So then clearly the heirs are not responsible to
compensate in that case. So the point is ראובן Reuven? is dead.
I don't know if that means being so clear, meaning like they
got the benefit. In other words, if their estate is now worth
a hundred dollars more because of the... if their father borrowed a
thousand dollars and didn't leave over land, like, that's a question whether
בעל חוב Ba'al chov can be goveh from the יורשים yorshim from
only from קרקע karka or even from מטלטלין, but there's certainly an
opinion that he can only be goveh from קרקע, karka, right? Same
idea. They were enriched by that thousand dollars the father borrowed and
now, but because there's no lien, the guy can't collect from the...
so anyway, we're just going to go with that for now. This
is a issue about the tenth פרק perek of בבא קמא Bava
Kamma or the ninth פרק, perek, we're not going to, we're just
going to accept for here what's being presented to us. But this
whole issue is expanded in that tenth פרק, perek, excuse me, of
בבא קמא. Bava Kamma. So, ראובן Reuven, stole, he died. Okay? Because
he died, שמעון Shimon. is never going to get compensated. Because שמעון
Shimon. is never going to get compensated and he's not going to
get his cow back because it was sold to לוי, so it's
יאוש ושינוי רשות, ye'ush v'shinui reshus. he can be a witness between
whether it belongs to יהודה or belongs to לוי. But if it
was land and he can retrieve his land, he can't be a
witness. Okay, so that's what הגמרא ha'gemara says. דמית גזלן, demis gazlan,
the גזלן died. דתנן, detnan, we taught, הגוזל ומאכיל את בניו, hagozel
u'ma'achil es banav, somebody who steals and then feeds the food that
he stole to his kids, והניח לפניהם v'heniach lifneihem or he left
the food behind, after he whatever he stole, after he had died,
פטורים מלשלם, pturim milishalem, they don't have to pay. Now, the והניח
לפניהם v'heniach lifneihem should upset you. What do you mean they don't
have to pay? The cow is still there in the yard. Why
do they not have to ever give it back? So it might
mean he left it for them when he died and then they
ate it, which we're talking about like food let's say, and therefore
they don't have to pay because it's no longer around, or it
might be as we'll see in a minute, that it's a case
of יאוש ושינוי רשות. ye'ush v'shinui reshus, He stole the cow, he
died, he stole the cow, there was יאוש, he died, it went
on to the heirs, that's like a שינוי רשות. Right. So now
they don't have to give it back. Okay, so anyway, but the
point being the heirs don't have to give it back. פטורים מלשלם.
pturim milishalem. So therefore, ah, so now we've got a case that
שמעון Shimon. can testify. ראובן Reuven is dead. He's not getting his
money back, he's not getting his cow back, he can testify. But
if it was land, then he can't testify because he could still
now try to get his land back and it matters to him
who is holding onto it. Correct. So now הגמרא ha'gemara says, one
minute. Once we're talking about the fact that ראובן Reuven died, so
הגמרא ha'gemara says, ולוקמה ביורש, v'lokmah b'yoresh, where am I? Yeah, I
know, I just missed my place. Okay, ולוקמה ביורש. v'lokmah b'yoresh. So
one minute, if ראובן Reuven died, what happens when ראובן Reuven dies?
He has heirs, okay, and does anybody know one of the names
of the sons of ראובן? Reuven בני ראובן חנוך ופלוא. bnei reuven
hanoch u'palu. Thank you, excellent. חנוך. Hanoch. Okay, so he died and
it was a case of יורש. yoresh. Okay, so if you're saying
that ראובן Reuven actually died, okay, if that's really the case הברייתא
ha'beraisa is dealing with, then it would not have to have a
case of him selling it to לוי. Because הברייתא ha'beraisa wanted to
have a case that it was chattel that he couldn't get back
because it was יאוש ושינוי רשות, ye'ush v'shinui reshus. and therefore שמעון
Shimon's can testify. And you're saying the only reason שמעון Shimon's doesn't
have a stake is because ראובן Reuven is dead and he's not
getting his money back. But if ראובן Reuven, is dead, then the
cow passed on to his son, and that's your יאוש ושינוי רשות.
ye'ush v'shinui reshus, So that itself could be your scenario. Why did
you have to... since the scenario demands that ראובן Reuven is dead
and you want the scenario also to be that it changed hands
and therefore right there's no because it changed hands therefore שמעון Shimon.
is not getting the cow back, you didn't have to have him
sell it. You just have to have him die and pass it
on to a son. Well, they were working up to his dying
before. That's what הגמרא ha'gemara was working up, but it's a claim
about what הברייתא ha'beraisa said. So if הברייתא ha'beraisa is really talking
that ראובן is dead, then הברייתא ha'beraisa in order that שמעון Shimon,
is not going to get paid back, then it would not have
to have him sell it. It should have just talked about his
son and that's why he's not getting his cow back. So הגמרא
ha'gemara says ולוקמה ביורש, v'lokmah b'yoresh, so just focus on the יורש.
yoresh. הניחא למאן דאמר, hanicha l'man d'amar, so that's good according to
the one that says רשות יורש לאו כרשות לוקח דמי, reshus yoresh
lav k'reshus lokeach dami, that when a יורש yoresh inherits it's not
like selling it to another person. This principle of יאוש ושינוי רשות,
giving up hope and then changing hands and you're not going to
get it back, that's only when you really sell it to a
third party. When a father dies and passes it on to his
son, that's just considered a continuation of ownership. So if you say
that when he dies and passes it on to חנוך Hanoch his
son, it's a continuation of ownership, then שמעון Shimon can still get
his cow back. Right? So that's why we have to have him
sell it to לוי. But there's an opinion that says that when
he bequeaths it, when he dies and חנוך Hanoch inherits it, it
is a change of possession, and according to that, who needs לוי
in the picture? Okay. We're getting an הלכה. halacha. Yeah, would it
validate the לוי case or not? Correct, explain why it was necessary.
Okay, אלא למאן דאמר רשות יורש כרשות לוקח דמי מאי איכא למימר.
ela l'man d'amar reshus yoresh k'reshus lokeach dami mai ika l'meimar. But
if the יורש yoresh is like a third party, you did not
need לוי. So you have this whole complicated way of explaining this
with שמעון, Shimon. ראובן, לוי, etc., sold, da-da-da-da-da, and that is... explains
the difference between land and chattel. But really, you have to go
through a lot of hoops and you gotta say ראובן is dead.
And then once you're saying ראובן is dead, you really didn't need
the selling yet according to at least one opinion. So this is
starting to make less and less sense. That's point number one. Number
two, says גמרא, Gemara ועוד קשיא ליה לאביי, ve-od kashya lei le-Abaye,
אביי's Abaye got also another problem with this. מפני שאחריותו עליו, it
says that שמעון can't testify because the אחריות achrayus is on him.
What do you mean the אחריות achrayus is on him? He can't
testify because he might stand to gain from the whole way in
which the court case plays out. So מאי? מפני שאחריותו עליו ואין
אחריותו עליו מיבעי ליה. mifnei she-achrayuto alav ve-ein achrayuto alav mibayei lei.
What it should just be saying is he can't testify in the
case of the land because the land can ultimately revert to him.
He might be able to get the land back. He can testify
in the case of the cow because it's not going to go
back to him. So the word אחריות achrayus is a completely wrong
word here. The reason שמעון can't testify, besides for this is talking
about ראובן and this is שמעון, the reason שמעון can't testify is
because he might get that land back. That has nothing to do
though with those words מפני שאחריותו עליו. Did he ever אחריות achrayus
on the mountain on the cow? Yes, but that still is not
the right word for this case. This case it's not about liability,
it's about getting it back. So we're going to get rid of
this entire complicated case which was such a crazy construct and now
we're going to get to what clearly was פשט pshat of the
ברייתא. So you're going to be so simple, you're going to wonder
why the גמרא didn't say this to begin with. Says גמרא says
like this: אלא כי דרבין בר שמואל. ela ki de-Rabin bar Shmuel.
It must be the right way to read this ברייתא is like
רבין בר שמואל, Rabin bar Shmuel, דאמר רבין בר שמואל משמיה דשמואל,
de-amar Rabin bar Shmuel mishmei de-Shmuel, in the name of שמואל, Shmuel,
המוכר שדה לחברו שלא באחריות, ha-mocher sadeh le-chavero shelo be-achrayus, אין מעיד
לו עליה, מפני שמעמידה בפני בעל חובו. ein meid lo aleha mifnei
she-maamidah bifnei ba'al chovo. Now you might remember this. Here we go.
Here's ראובן and שמעון. He's going to sell שמעון a field שלא
באחריות, shelo be-achrayus, means without insurance. Now somebody else, we'll keep it
with יהודה, he's the troublemaker. He comes and he says that field
is mine. Can שמעון, ראובן testify that no, no, it's rightfully שמעון's?
So let's consider two cases. One case is that he's insured the
field for שמעון and he says if somehow you lose that field
and it's taken because of my debts or because it wasn't mine,
whatever, I'm going to reimburse you. So if there was אחריות, achrayus,
could he testify against יהודה that it's שמעון's? This is, yeah, why
not? Well, think about it. He has insured the field, he sells
the field to שמעון and he's insured it. And he said if
you ever lose the field I will reimburse you. And now יהודה
comes and says, oh but no, no, because then he'd have to
reimburse. Obviously. So if it's with אחריות achrayus he obviously cannot testify.
Let's say it's without אחריות. achrayus. He has no liability to reimburse
שמעון. Then you might think he can testify. What does he care
whether יהודה takes it or not? He's not going to have to
reimburse שמעון. But the חידוש chiddush is he cannot testify. Why? מפני
שמעמידה בפני בעל חובו. mifnei she-maamidah bifnei ba'al chovo. Because we had
this, because this guy here, we'll have this guy מרדכי. Mordechai. He
lent him a hundred dollars. Make it a thousand. So he, even
though if it gets taken from שמעון he won't have to reimburse
שמעון, he wants it to stay in שמעון's hands as the field
he sold שמעון as opposed to the field that was always יהודה's.
Because if it's the field he sold שמעון, when מרדכי Mordechai comes
for his thousand dollars, he can collect. Why wouldn't מרדכי Mordechai have
to take it from ראובן? From ראובן, but ראובן doesn't have any
cash on hand, but מרדכי Mordechai has liens on the land. So
since this land was once ראובן's and that gave מרדכי Mordechai liens
on the land and then it got sold, מרדכי Mordechai can now
get that field from שמעון. But if the field was always יהודה's,
then ראובן is going to owe מרדכי Mordechai the money and מרדכי's
Mordechai debt will never have been paid off. So he would much
rather it have been his field that was sold to שמעון rather
than to have been יהודה's field. So he can't testify. So that's
if there's no אחריות? achrayus? If there's no אחריות. achrayus. If there
is אחריות, achrayus, it's obvious why he can't testify. But even if
there's no אחריות, achrayus, he can't because he'd rather it be like
this, cause then he can, that can work for his creditors. In
the case that he's a debtor to someone. Right, but we're going
to have to assume that that might always be the case. אין
מעיד לו עליה מפני שמעמידה בפני בעל חובו. mifnei she-maamidah bifnei ba'al
chovo. Now, how does that then explain this case? This case now
becomes a lot easier. מכר לו את הבית, machar lo es ha-bayis,
ראובן sold the house to שמעון. אין מעיד לו עליו, ein meid
lo alav, ראובן can't be מעיד on it. יהודה's now claiming it's
his house. ראובן cannot be מעיד that no, no, no, that really
belongs to שמעון. Why? מפני שאחריותו עליו. אחריותו עליו achrayuto alav does
not mean אחריותו עליו achrayuto alav that he has to reimburse שמעון.
That is not the case. אחריותו עליו it's a little bit of
a twist of that language, but it means because there could be
liens on this land. מפני really means like מפני שיש אחריות על
mifnei she-yesh achrayus al Okay, because there might be liens, which is
what אחריות *achrayut* normally means on this land. So he cannot keep
it in the hands of שמעון *Shimon* because there might be liens,
but let's say it's not a piece of land. Let's say it's
a cow. Okay. Mordechai has no liens on Reuven's
cows. Liens are on land. So if he sold this cow to
שמעון *Shimon* and יהודה *Yehuda* is claiming that the cow was always
his, and he's not going to have to reimburse שמעון *Shimon*, okay,
for that, he can testify that it's שמעון *Shimon*'s. Why? He can,
because מפני שאין אחריותו עליו *mipnei she-ein achrayuto alav*, because Mordechai has
no liens on the cow. That's a very nice super simple read
of that ברייתא *braita*. After that very complicated גמרא *Gemara* it's like,
man, why didn't they say that in the beginning? Yes. Okay, two
things. One is this also has the advantage of not being sad
because יהודה *Yehuda* is still alive, he didn't die. ברוך השם *Baruch
Hashem*. Second thing is, I keep on hacking away at this. We
keep on translating אחריות *achrayut* as this liens on it, and I
keep on saying to myself, what's the translation difference between שעבוד *shibud*
and אחריות *achrayut*? Yeah, there isn't one. I don't know, I don't
know if I mean אחריות *achrayut* is no, שעבוד *shibud* is a
more narrower, שעבוד *shibud* literally is only liens, אחריות *achrayut* can mean
a lot of things. It can mean I accept liability if it
goes wrong, I'm accepting insurance, but it could also mean that the
liens that are a result of the אחריות *achrayut*. So אחריות *achrayut*
is a more generic word, שעבוד *shibud* is a more technical is
a more specific word. Yes. Getting back to the land, ברייתא *braita*,
so I guess we have to assume that there was no שטר
shtar *shtar* because otherwise it could have even was שלא באחריות *she-lo
b'achrayut*, but when we say אחריות טעות סופר *achrayut taut sofer*, it
would have been באחריות *b'achrayut*. No, let me clarify, אחריות טעות סופר
*achrayut taut sofer* means when I lend you money, I'm assumed to
have and here the אחריות *achrayut* again means liens, I'm assumed to
have liens on your land even if it wasn't written into the
שטר *shtar*. The question about whether I insure, which is a different
use of the word אחריות *achrayut*, I insure the sale, that's not
a question of טעות סופר *taut sofer*, that has to explicitly be
stated that I'm insuring the sale. Even if there's a contract, I
am not I'm not insuring right, I have to explicitly state that
I'm insuring you against indemnity, whatever no, that's a different point, I'm
insuring you if it gets stolen. Right, but as if it's a
loan and there's a contract, we assume that there are liens on
the קרקע karka *karka*, that's a different liens are different than insurance.
Okay. Yes. So we're assuming then that the original issue of the
land to begin with did not involve a שטר *shtar*, is that
what we're saying? No, it might have, because if there was a
שטר *shtar* involved, wouldn't that automatically prove that the land didn't belong
no, it just proves that I wrote a שטר *shtar* and gave
it to you, but maybe it was stolen in my possession to
begin with. Okay. Right? I can write a שטר *shtar* on land
that's not mine, right, it's like the guy sells you the Brooklyn
Bridge, here I'll write you out a receipt. All right. So, all
right, so the גמרא *Gemara* says, all right. אבל בפרה וטלית לא
*Aval b'parah v'talit lo*, but if it was a cow that was
sold and he doesn't have to reimburse שמעון *Shimon* if it gets
taken, then he can testify, because there's no liens that Mordechai could
have on it. He's not it doesn't matter to him whether it's
Shimon's or Yehuda's, it's not going to be something he can give
Mordechai, Mordechai can collect from. לא *Lo*. לא מבעיא *Lo mibaya*, it
goes without saying, בסתמא *b'stama*, that in a normal case there's no
liens on chattel, liens are only on land and not on chattel.
דלא משתעבדי ליה *D'la mishtabdei lei*, that it's not it's not encumbered,
there are no liens. מאי טעמא mai taama, *Mai ta'ama*, מטלטלי נינהו
*metaltlei ninhu*, because they're chattel, ומטלטלי לבעל חוב לא משתעבדי *u'metaltlei l'ba'al
chov lo mishtabdei*, and chattel is not encumbered to the בעל חוב
baal chov, *ba'al chov* for the reasons the most obvious reason is
because you can always hide your chattel but you can't hide your
land. But also so it's basically where the normal creditor assumes that
he has a surety and he knows he'll be able to collect
from, right, and it also has something to do with the fact
of the sort of more public nature. If you if there was
liens on על מטלטלין *al metaltelin*, then you'd always be afraid to
buy anything in the store because somebody might have a lien on
it, right? So land which is a much bigger purchase, much bigger
deal, and again there could be more publicity about it and so
on, there we can sort of say you have to be buyer
beware and check out for liens, but there are no they're not
going to be liens on chattel. Okay, so that's why it's okay
to testify in that case. That's certainly if it was sold even
without anything being stated explicitly. דאפילו דכתב ליה *D'afillu d'katav lei* מגלימא
דעל כתפיה *mi-glima d'al katfei*, now this is very interesting, you're going
to you might notice some of this language that we're going to
deal with in this דף *daf* from the כתובה ketubah, *ketubah*. Well,
from the כתובה ketubah? *ketubah*, right, it says like this, the language
of the כתובה ketubah, *ketubah* is that I am obligating myself to
you even from the coat off of from the garment right off
my back, the shirt off my back, so that sounds like there's
a lien on chattel. No, הני מילי דאיתנהו בעינייהו *hani mili d'itneihu
b'eineihu*, that's only if it's under the possession of the person who
actually owns the money, they're still around. אבל ליתנהו בעינייהו *Aval leitneihu
b'eineihu*, if they're not still around, meaning it's not that it got
destroyed, but it's no longer the person's possession, לא *lo*, there's no
lien. Wait, so you're saying there could be a lien on the
מטלטלין *metaltelin*, on the garment? If I come to collect money you
owe me, and you don't have any cash and you don't have
any land, or even if you do have land or whatever, I
can collect from your I can just take your car, I can
seize your TV, I can seize your shirt, but that sounds like
a שעבוד *shibud*. No, that's why the גמרא addresses it. I, the
בעל חוב, baal chov do have a right to take the shirt
off your back. But if that shirt off your back is no
longer on your back, if the shirt has been sold, then I
can't take it. But that's true of land? No, you can take
land back. But you can't take a shirt. You can take a
different shirt though. I can take a different shirt off his back.
Okay, so it's נגלימא דעל כתפיה. niglima d'al katfei. I can take
the shirt off your back. I can't take it off somebody else's
back. I appreciate being bullied. Okay, but you can't take it at
night, right? You'd have to give it back. Yes, but that's a
different discussion. All right, let's move on. So, the בעל חוב has
a right to collect from any property that's in the possession of
the debtor, but if it's not in the possession of the debtor,
he can only collect from land. That's in a סתם stam case.
That, okay, that goes without saying. אלא אפילו עשאו אפותיקי, ela afilu
asao apotiki, even in a case here where ראובן said to מרדכי,
Mordechai, he said to him, I will explicitly write out that thousand
dollars that you can collect it from my cow Bessie here, I
know you've had your eye on her, you think she'll make a
lot of money in the market or whatever, I'm going to give
you special rights to collect from Bessie. Now, you might think that
that means that even if Bessie gets sold. But no, that is
only while Bessie is under my possession. So what good does the
אפותיקי apotiki do to מרדכי? Mordechai? Because if I didn't have the
אפותיקי, apotiki, you'd try to give me some of your weak link
cows or you try to give me other stuff. I want Bessie.
That's what I want. I don't want anything else. So the אפותיקי
apotiki works to allow מרדכי Mordechai to collect from it while it's
in the possession of ראובן, but once it's sold, anything that is
not קרקע karka, does not, the liens do not go beyond that
original person. Okay, so does אפותיקי apotiki refer to a person or
it's always a, it's like a written document, right? No, it's always
a, it's always a written document. It's a lien that designates a
particular thing. Okay. אלא אפילו עשאו אפותיקי, ela afilu asao apotiki, even,
I mean, maybe you're saying the אפותיקי apotiki is the thing that
is the אפותיקי. apotiki. Right. Even if this was made the אפותיקי,
apotiki, the collateral, the designated collateral, that would be a good word
for אפותיקי. apotiki. Even if this was the designated collateral, okay, נמי
לא, nami lo, it still couldn't collect it once it wasn't in
his hands. מאי טעמא דרבא? mai taama d'Rava? דאמר רבא, d'amar Rava,
רבא Rava says,
עשה עבדו אפותיקי, asa avdo apotiki, if you made your slave designated
collateral, ומכרו, umacharo, and you sold it, it's not in your hands,
בעל חוב גובה הימנו, baal chov goveh heimenu, the creditor can collect
because again, it's assumed that there is more knowledge of who the
original owners were and therefore somebody coming to buy a slave would
also like, you know, be able
to, well actually let's read it because the גמרא is going to
say it. Okay. מכרו בעל חוב גובה הימנו שור וחמור אפותיקי ומכרו
אין בעל חוב גובה הימנו. macharo baal chov goveh heimenu shor v'chamor
apotiki umacharo ein baal chov goveh heimenu. But if it's not a
slave, if it's any other type of a chattel, then the creditor
cannot collect from it once it's not in the person's hands, even
if it's designated collateral. מאי טעמא, what's the reason? האי אית ליה
קלא והאי לית ליה קלא. hai it lei kala v'hai leit lei
kala. One of them is well-known and the other is not well-known.
What does this mean? Look at the רשב"ם Rashbam about six lines
down in the narrow lines.
אית ליה קלא אפסידו לקוחות אנפשייהו ולית ליה קלא פסידא ולא ידעו
הלקוחות להיזהר. it lei kala afsidu lokachot anafsheihu v'leit lei kala psida
v'lo yadu halokachot lehizaher. Okay, so for some reason that if I
and I, you know again, I don't fully get this, but if
I went ahead and I borrowed money from דוב Dov and I
designated my slave as the collateral, then people will know that this
slave has been designated as collateral. So therefore, if somebody comes to
buy the slave, they'll be able to find it out. Whereas if
I designated my cow as collateral, people won't know. Again, I'm not
exactly sure why that is. What's the קשיא kushya from the קול
kol without knowing? Isn't עבד eved הוקש לקרקע? hokush l'karka? Right, so
תוספות Tosafot discusses that, but even if you normally don't put slaves
in the same category as קרקע, this distinction would still hold. Okay,
that's exactly what, what? I don't know. I don't know enough about
the societal norms or the realities, but maybe it is because of
that. Real estate and slaves are seen as the major possession that
defines a person's status, you know, and wealth. So therefore, if I
have said, you know, if I put my slave up for collateral
or my land, people know about it. That's a big deal. But
if I just put a cow up for collateral, people don't know
about it. Is that a house? No, a house is land. Is
it possible that it's really concrete at some level of its development
legally, like slaves talk and things don't talk? So slaves can talk
about the fact that they're put up. Maybe. Say, I so-and-so, that's
good, or for I've been
or not yet, I mean I've been put up as collateral. But
that assumes the slave knows what the master has been doing in
his business deals, which is a big question I would highly doubt,
but okay, but I hear the point. Anyway, so, so now we've
got it. He sells land, he can't testify because that land, it
benefits him that it's in שמעון's possession because מרדכי Mordechai can collect.
He sells chattel, he can't testify even if it was made designated
collateral for מרדכי, Mordechai, once it's in שמעון's hands,
מרדכי Mordechai cannot collect from it. Right, so the גמרא *Gemara* says
like this. Okay, וליחוש דילמא אקני ליה מטלטלי אגב
מקרקעי *v'leikhush dilma aknei leh metaltalei agav
mekarkai*.
One minute. There's ways in which מרדכי Mordechai *Mordechai* can have collateral
on Bessy. How can that be? Because what he could do is
what ראובן *Reuven* could do, what ראובן *Reuven* could do when he
borrows the $1,000 is he basically writes in the document where he
says I borrowed a thousand dollars, ראובן *Reuven* borrowed a thousand dollars
from מרדכי Mordechai. *Mordechai*, and it says and he basically gave מרדכי
*Mordechai* liens on his land and with the liens on his land
he gave him liens on his chattel on Bessy. Okay, so therefore
even though you cannot directly create liens on the מטלטלין *metaltelin*, even
if you wrote it in a שטר *shtar*, you didn't do it,
right? We just said even if you made it an אפותיקי *apoteiki*.
But if you bundled it together with land, and again I can't
understand how this protects buyers once this is a possibility, but we
won't worry about that right now, if you bundled it together with
land there could be liens. So why aren't we afraid that ראובן
*Reuven* when he borrowed the money bundled Bessy together with his land
as something that מרדכי *Mordechai* has a lien on? Okay, and therefore
even if ראובן *Reuven* sold and therefore even if he sold it
מרדכי *Mordechai* could collect and he benefits from testifying. Now by the
way, this is another phrase from the כתובה *Ketubah*. It's a phrase,
so he can collect from Bessy or from the land equally? Yeah,
does it make a difference? Does he have to collect from the
land first? I don't know, I don't know. Anyway, so also in
other words, אגב קרקע *agav karka* you assume anything that's on the
land goes along with—no, no, no. This would have to be explicit.
Okay, so anyway this is also part of the language of the
כתובה *Ketubah*, right? Part of the language of the כתובה *Ketubah* which
is a standard language of a שטר *shtar*. First of all was
ואפילו מגלימא דעל כתפיה *v'afilu miglima d'al katfei* which we just said
means only while you're in possession. But it also says דקנאי ודעתיד
אנא למקני *d'kanai
v'da'atid ana l'miknei*. Everything I own and everything I will buy. Okay,
now דקנאי *d'kanai* means everything that I own, that's the language of
the גמרא *Gemara*, all my possessions including my מטלטלין *metaltelin*. Okay, so
this was like a standard language of a שטר *shtar* if you
really wanted to give somebody strength. Okay, again I don't know how
this protects people who are going to buy your מטלטלין *metaltelin*. Okay,
but that's the question of the גמרא *Gemara*. Okay. Which means liens
in other words, that the מטלטלין *metaltelin* would be liens? Yeah. So
the גמרא *Gemara* says like this—no not just Bessy, it's—the שטר *shtar*
has to give everything? It could be everything, it could be just
some things, it depends on what you designate. If you say all
my מטלטלין *metaltelin* it's all, if you say on these then it's
on those. So you're saying that that in the כתובה *Ketubah* it
is a combination of both and therefore the גלימא *glima* you can't—would
it extend to the—to
the—I mean the language of the כתובה *Ketubah* here, let me pull
up the נוסח *nusach* of the כתובה *Ketubah*. I assume דקנאי ודעתיד
אנא למקני *d'kanai v'da'atid ana l'miknei* refers to מטלטלין *metaltelin*. Yeah, maybe
it doesn't. I'm jumping a little bit ahead in the גמרא *Gemara*
because the גמרא *Gemara* is going to get to the דעתיד אנא
למקני *d'atid ana l'miknei* which does refer which does refer to מטלטלין
*metaltelin* but hold on let me just—let me
just—let me just get—but you can use Bessy for both though?
What?
If he's going to get there then—well the גמרא *Gemara* is going
to get there with the עתיד אנא למקני *atid ana l'miknei*. Whether
it refers to טלטלין *taltelin* or קרקע *karka*. All right, let's see.
This is pulling up, give me two more seconds here. Shh, quiet
people. All right. So anyway let's see while this is pulling up
the נוסח *nusach* of the כתובה *Ketubah*, let's read the גמרא *Gemara*'s
answer. If he sells property, can he still have a lien on?
Yeah, that's the whole point of the—the whole point of the lien.
Yeah. So how should the person who bought ever—he'd have to know
that—that's the point, that's the point, how does it protect buyers if
he
doesn't know—that's—all right, I don't know, this isn't coming up. Okay anyway.
So the גמרא *Gemara* says like this—if you say in the שטר
*shtar* that has the land sale, then when you're doing a search
for land? Right, that might be if there was a copy of
the שטר *shtar* somewhere. The problem is that I don't know of
any evidence that there's a copy of the שטר *shtar*, you know?
That's the problem. All right, so anyway that you know there's no
central repository. Okay, wait here we go, here's the נוסח *nusach* of
the כתובה *Ketubah*. It says okay okay, וקבילית
עלי
ועל ירתי בתראי *v'kabbilit
alai v'al yartai batrai* me and my heirs after me, להתפרע מכל
שפר ארג נכסין *l'hitpara mikol shefar arag nichsin* from all of my
possessions, וקנינין *v'kinyanin* all of my possessions, sounds like it's not limited
to קרקע *karka*, דאית לי תחות כל שמיא *d'it li t'chot kol
shamaya* under the entire heavens, דקנאי *d'kanai* that I own now, ודעתיד
אנא למקני *v'da'atid ana l'miknei* and that I will own. Oh, it's
explicit. I don't know what I was thinking. נכסין דאית להון אחריות
ודלית להון אחריות *nechasin d'it l'hon achrayut u'd'leit l'hon achrayut* which basically
is land or מטלטלין *metaltelin*,
כולהון *kulhon* all of them, יהון אחראין וערבאין למפרע מנהון שטר כתובתא
דא ונדוניא דין ותוספתא דא *yehon achrain v'arvain l'mifra min-hon shtar ketubta
da u'nedunya den v'tosefta da*. So there you go. A שטר כתובה
*shtar Ketubah* basically bundles the מטלטלין *metaltelin* with the קרקע *karka* and
not only that this is what we're going to get to, things
that I own and things that you'll own in the future which
we're going to get to in a minute. So now the
גמרא *Gemara* continues. That we're going to get to next. To be
clear, are you saying that therefore if
any married person who sells anything, right, is selling everything with a
right, in principle, yes, in principle. Okay. We just need to start
enforcing it. There you go. Okay, so the גמרא says like this,
okay. For the benefit of the room, people, people, thank you, being
uncontrolled with my invitation.
All right, so the גמרא
says וליחוש דלמא אקני ליה מטלטלי אגב מקרקעי דאמר רבא יקני ליה
מטלטלי אגב מקרקעי קני מקרקעי קני מטלטלי. ve-le-chush dilma akni lei metalteli
agav mekarkei de-amar Rava yakni lei metalteli agav mekarkei kani mekarkei kani
metalteli. It uses the word קנין kinyan but it means there's a
lien both on the land and on the chattel. ואמר רב חסדא
והוא דכתב ליה דלא כאסמכתא ודלא כטופסי דשטרי. ve-amar Rav Chisda ve-hu
de-chtiv lei de-la ke-as-machtah u-de-la ke-tofshei de-shtarei. If you wanted to really
say I really mean it, I'm not just being flowery, okay, then
you have to say I really mean it, of course what happens
if when the line I really mean it becomes part of the
טופסא דשטרא? tofsa de-shtra? Okay, טופסא דשטרא tofsa de-shtra is like the
boilerplate, and that's what we have at the end of the כתובה,
right? Exactly. דלא כאסמכתא ודלא כטופסי דשטרי. de-la ke-as-machtah ve-lo ke-tofshei de-shtarei.
That's at the end of the כתובה?
Yes, yeah. I had no idea what that means. Okay. It's not
like I'm just סתם, stam, not being serious, and it's not boilerplate,
I really mean it. Okay, so the key word here was that
was the other line of the
כתובה, נכסים דאית להון אחריות ודלית להון אחריות. nechasim de-it le-hon achrayut
u-de-leit le-hon achrayut. That's the most explicit line. I mean, it says
everything I own, תחת כל שמיא. tachat kol shamaya. Okay, so there
you go, you bundled it all together, and we're going to get
to that line, and you said that line at the end, you
said you really, you really mean it. Okay. So the גמרא says,
anyway, so why aren't we concerned that that happened here? So the
גמרא says הכא במאי עסקינן כגון שלקח ומכר לאלתר. hacha be-mai askinan
kigon she-lakach u-machar le-altar. Ah,
no. The case here was he bought Bessie and he sold her
right away to שמעון. And therefore, in that case, we're not afraid
he didn't have a chance to borrow money from מרדכי between the
two. Okay. So since we saw him buy Bessie and sell it
directly to שמעון, and there could have been no loan, lien between
the two, he didn't borrow money, then he can testify. So the
גמרא says, but what if he had a loan outstanding from before?
Of course, presumably we assume a loan only works on stuff that's
in the possession once the loan, the loan doesn't work on stuff
that, well, that's what the גמרא's going to say. Okay.
Because the assumption is the loan only works on property that is
in the borrower's possession at the time of the loan. That's how
liens are created. New property that the borrower take, you know, sort
of takes possession of after the loan, there are no liens on.
Although you could have written that just like I wrote it in
the—okay, so I gave it away. That's what we're getting to. Okay.
But the normal assumption is, I lend you money, right, I have
a lien on your current property, not on your future property. So
therefore, in this case, I bought Bessie and I sold her, previous
liens wouldn't be relevant and there wasn't a chance to get a
new loan. So that would be the case that I'd be able
to testify. So the גמרא says וליחוש
דלמא דאקני הוא. ve-le-chush dilma de-akni hu. One minute, why aren't we
concerned that you did דאקני, de-akni, דקנינא ודעתידנא למיקני, de-kanina u-de-atid-na le-mikni,
that you basically wrote when you borrowed the money, your lien will
be effective not just on property I have now, but on property
I'll have in the future. Now there's a question similar to questions:
are you able to do that? You normally can't sell a דבר
שלא בא לעולם, davar she-lo ba la-olam, can you create a שיעבוד
shibbud on something שלא בא לעולם? she-lo ba la-olam? So that's what
the גמרא doesn't know. Should we say שמע מינה דאיקני קנה ומכר
קנה והוריש לא משתעבד, shma mina de-ikni kana u-machar kana ve-horish lo
mishtaabed,
that if you wrote in your שטר דאיקני de-ikni that it—the lien
should apply on stuff I will get in the future, then it
really is not effective? If you bought it and sold it, and
then bought it or bequeathed it, the person would not be able
to collect it if it's still in your possession, but he couldn't
collect it if it's in the hand of another person. So meaning,
should we say that this language that I will buy in the
future, דעתידנא למיקני, de-atid-na le-mikni, which is just a long way of
saying דאיקני, de-ikni, things I will buy, does not really create liens?
Because if they really created liens, we'd have to be afraid that
there were liens on Bessie and he couldn't testify. So the גמרא
says לא צריכה, lo tzricha, no, maybe it does create liens. So
how can he testify about Bessie? דקאמרי עדים ידעינן ביה בהאי דלא
הוה ליה ארעא מעולם. de-ka-amri edim yadinan beh be-hai de-lo hava leh
ara me-olam. Okay, this
is getting more and more convoluted. Okay. So witnesses say, we know
ראובן never in his life owned property. And I don't know how
they knew that, they were with him from the day he was
born until now. And since we know he never in his life
owned property, there was no way he could bundle a lien on
property with Bessie to מרדכי. He never owned real estate. And since
he never owned real estate, there was never going to be a
lien on Bessie, because it only works when you bundle it with
real estate. So the גמרא *Gemara* says one minute. והאמר רב פפא
*Veha'amar Rav Papa*, but doesn't רב פפא *Rav Papa* say, אף על
גב דאמור רבנן המוכר שדה לחבירו שלא באחריות ובא בעל חוב וטרפה
אינו חוזר עליו *Af al gav de'amor Rabbanan hamocher sadeh lechavero shelo
beachrayut uva ba'al chov utrafah eino chozer alav*? Okay, now we're going
to get back to, okay, so that was very, very complicated to
explain how there's no lien on Bessie. Okay, but the simple idea
is we generally assume there's no lien on מטלטלין *metaltelin* and therefore
that's why he can testify in this case. However, as you see
from the נוסח הכתובה *nusach haktubah* and תוספות *Tosafot* talks about this,
it might have begun to be that this became to be standard
נוסח השטר *nusach hashtar*. Standard נוסח השטר *nusach hashtar* started to say,
oh yes, you have it with מטלטלין *metaltelin* and it's דלא כאסמכתא
ודלא כטופסי דשטרי *dela ke'asmachta udela ketofsey deshtarey* and everything I'll get
in the future. And then the point is when all of this
turns into boilerplate, does it really mean it anymore? Okay, but anyway,
so that's really the question that תוספות *Tosafot* discusses. That gets back
to your question, David, right? How much does it mean it once
it all becomes boilerplate? Okay, but anyway, the basic point is there
are no liens on Bessie. There is a lien on the land
so he can't testify on the land. He can't testify unless he
cannot testify on the land. Now,
we are going to now discuss the basic point about this issue
that if יהודה *Yehuda* came
and said it was his, okay, and he says you stole it,
he makes a claim against it that
ראובן *Reuven* can't testify by the land but he can testify by
Bessie. Why can he testify by Bessie? Because he doesn't benefit because
there's no liens on it. Okay. And he says, hey, I didn't
sell it to you with any insurance. But here's going to be
the problem. Who cares whether you sold it to שמעון *Shimon* with
insurance? If it turns out that Bessie always belonged to יהודה *Yehuda*,
that's something known as a מקח טעות *mekach taut*, right? שמעון *Shimon*
says, you sold me something you didn't own. I don't need insurance
to get reimbursed for that. The whole sale was under false premises.
So how can ראובן *Reuven* ever testify about Bessie even if there's
no liens from מרדכי *Mordechai* by saying it's שמעון *Shimon*? If יהודה
*Yehuda* actually genuinely proves it was always his, he's going to have
to reimburse him even if there was no insurance, okay, because it
was a false sale. So let's take a look at that. גמרא
*Gemara* says, והאמר רב פפא *Veha'amar Rav Papa*, yeah, והאמר רב פפא
*Veha'amar Rav Papa*,
didn't רב פפא *Rav Papa* say, אף על גב דאמרו רבנן המוכר
שדה לחבירו שלא באחריות ובא בעל חוב וטרפה אינו חוזר עליו *Af
al gav de'amru Rabbanan hamocher sadeh lechavero shelo beachrayut uva ba'al chov
utrafah eino chozer alav*, that if you sold it without insurance and
then it was taken for payment of a debt, so you don't
have to reimburse, okay, אינו חוזר עליו *eino chozer alav*. נמצאת שאינה
שלו חוזר עליו *Nimtzet she'einah shelo chozer alav*. If it turns out
you never owned it, then you would have to reimburse. It was
a false sale. So how can you ever testify about Bessie here?
If it turns out it was a false sale, you never owned
it, you'll have to reimburse שמעון *Shimon*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says,
הכא במאי עסקינן במכיר בה שהיא בת חמורו *Hacha bemai askinan bemakir
bah shehi bat chamoro*. No, no, no. In this is a case
where שמעון *Shimon* says when he buys it from ראובן *Reuven*, and
the reason it says donkey is because there's going to be a
donkey in a case later on, but it means cow. שמעון *Shimon*
says to ראובן *Reuven*, let's say יהודה *Yehuda* comes and makes a
claim about this cow. And שמעון *Shimon* says to ראובן *Reuven* in
front of witnesses, ראובן *Reuven*, I know it was your cow. Like,
I saw, you know, its mother in your stable give birth to
this cow, okay? This cow's mother give birth to it. So I
know יהודה *Yehuda* is making this false claim against you. So שמעון
*Shimon* basically concedes to ראובן *Reuven* that it always was ראובן *Reuven*'s
cow. And once he's conceded that, if יהודה *Yehuda* somehow wins the
court case, because יהודה *Yehuda* can still win even if he is
lying or whatever, שמעון *Shimon* can't ask for his money back from
ראובן *Reuven*. Because he's admitted to ראובן *Reuven* that he knows it
was a good sale. Okay? So how can ראובן *Reuven* testify in
this case? He can testify because שמעון *Shimon* has admitted to him
that he knows it's a good sale. So once he knows that
this cow really belonged to ראובן *Reuven*, and once he's admitted that
to ראובן *Reuven*, right, then ראובן *Reuven* doesn't benefit from the fact
that it's שמעון *Shimon*'s and not יהודה *Yehuda*'s. If יהודה *Yehuda* were
to win, שמעון *Shimon* couldn't ask for his money back because שמעון
*Shimon* has conceded the fact that it always belonged to ראובן *Reuven*.
Okay? So במכיר בה שהיא בת חמורו *bemakir bah shehi bat chamoro*,
that שמעון *Shimon* has conceded the fact that it always belonged to
ראובן *Reuven* and therefore he's never going to be able to get
reimbursed. Essentially,
שמעון *Shimon* is collaborating—no, he's not. But I can't go there. רב
זביד Zvid *Rav Zvid* אמר *amar*, I have to read the next
line. אפילו נמצאת שאינה שלו אינו חוזר עליו *Afillu nimtzet she'einah shelo
eino chozer alav*. רב זביד *Rav Zvid* disagrees with the פשט *pshat*.
רב זביד *Rav Zvid* says, I don't care. Even if it turns
out that ראובן *Reuven* never owned it, you can't ask for your
money back. Why? דאמר ליה להכי זבינתי לך שלא באחריות *De'amar leh
lehachi zevinti lach shelo beachrayut*. That's why I didn't give you insurance.
Okay? It's buyer beware. The lack of insurance means even if it
turns out that for some reason, because first of all, like, you
know, I even if it turns out that somebody wins a claim
against me and proves that this property was theirs, first of all,
who knows they're telling the truth? Maybe they're the liars. But bottom
line is, that's what. Means to buy something without insurance. You're accepting
all of the risk, even the risk that it might not really
be mine. Okay? So there's an interesting debate in that case, if
you sold something and it was proven that it wasn't yours, okay,
whether you have to reimburse because maybe just because it was proven
in court doesn't mean that that was true, and could you say,
"I didn't give you insurance, I'm sorry, I'm not reimbursing," or no,
you do have to reimburse when it's proven it's not yours, and
that it makes it more complicated for ראובן to testify on behalf
of שמעון because then if it, if it is taken away, he'll
have to reimburse שמעון. Okay, we got through that difficult stuff. All
right, so now what זביד is saying is buyer beware.